世界时刻变化，没人知道发生着什么，
The world is changing, now no one knows what's going,
但是我们将到那里，揭示新闻，
but we'll be there, uncovering the news,
文化
culture
政治
some politics.
并且曝光现代社会的荒谬之事。
and expose the absurdity of the modern condition.
那个孩子拿着一个很大的枪，
That little child had a huge gun.
我之前从来没见过这种场面
I had never seen this just before.
看着像地球上的地狱
looks like a hell on Earth.
她们是人肉炸弹的自杀者，都是小孩。
They were the suicide bombers, they were kids.
这是我们眼中观察的世界
This is the world through our eyes
这是一个充满罪恶的世界。
This is the world of VICE.
嗨，我是 Shane Smith, 这里是纽约布鲁克林区的
VICE 系列节目的演播室。
Hi, I'm Shane Smith, we're here in the VICE offices in Brooklyn New York.
中国经济正在成长。
China is booming.
过去30年，中国经济一直保持着两位数的增涨速度。
It's economy has been growing with double digit growth for the last 3 decades.
事实上，据估计，中国会在 20年内超过美国，
成为世界上最大的经济体。
In fact, it's estimated that China will overtake the US as the world's largest economy in just 20 years.
但我们不知道的是，这个增涨的健康情况。
But what we don't know much about though, is the health of that growth.
有迹象表明，中国正在向 2008年震撼美国的房地产崩盘靠近。
There're signs that China is heading for the same kind of realistic collapse that rocked America in 2008.
我们派记者 Ryan Duffy 去看看世界上下一个很可能在现实中
出现的经济灾难会是什么样子的。
So we sent Ryan Duffy to see what the world's next realistic disaster might just look like.
道兰论坛  daolan.net  原创字幕
English subtitle comes from  daolan.net forum
欢迎观看中国现实中经济增长的面目。
Welcome to the face of China's realistic boom.
欢迎来到天东城，位于上海南部，中国最大的仿巴黎社区。
Welcome to TianDuCheng, China's biggest Paris playground just south of Shanghai.
这个仿巴黎社区有些能勾起人来看看的欲望，有几分人性的味道。
Paris is a little bit of to be desired, a little bit of several human meanings.
什么使得这个单纯的仿造巴黎社区变得有趣？
What makes this copycat Paris intersting?
它只是个单纯的仿造巴黎的社区吗？
Is it just the copycat Paris?
它是一个完全荒置的纯仿造巴黎的社区。
It is a completely abandoned copycat Paris.
用来做婚礼照相，猎奇之类的事情。
used for little more than wedding photos and curiosity seeking.
你怎么会选择在这拍结婚照的？
How did you choose to marry here?
这不是实际中的商业，现实里还没有一个商业。
It's not actually that business, not a business actually real.
哦，看看这些乱七八糟的玩意。
Oh... look at this realistic fuck.
在这个地点建造自由的埃菲尔铁塔，这个是一个好主意
So, this site, build this free impressive Gustave Eiffel Tower which is the fine idea and then
之后就开发了这一片目所能及的所有的土地，
developed all of this part of as far as the eye can see
这个主意一直很好，直到大家集体决定: 我不想住这。
which also a fine idea until everyone decide collectively: we don't want to live there.
房地产已经成为中国经济的主要增涨因素。
Real estate has been a major growth factor for the Chinese economy.
近些年大约占总 GDP 的 30%。
Accounting for about 30% of the country soaring GDP in recent years.
但许多这类建设已经处于投机过热了。
But a lot of this construction has been wildly speculated.
中国政府是会把这些工程算作经济增涨，
Sure, the Chinese government may count these projects as growth,
但问题是，中国只根据房屋建设来计算 GDP，
并非根据房屋销售情况。
but the problem is that China calculates GDP due property construction, not property sales.
人们讨论房地产市场对于中国 GDP 的影响，
People talked about the property market's effect to China's GDP.
诚然，近十年来，中国是出口型经济。
It's true that 10 years ago, China export led economy.
但现在，房地产已经成为中国 GDP 中最重要的影响因子。
but now these property has been the single most important factors to this.
房地产市场已经在很大程度上嵌入到中国整体的经济发展中。
the property market is very much embedded in the whole part of China's economy growth.
所有这些投机已经导致了一个过分饱和的市场。
All this speculation has led to a glutton market,
但在中国，投机商们把太多的关注点都放在了房地产上。
they're simply weight too much real estate in China.
这就导致了很多问题，类似这个已经建成5年的投资了
数十亿美元的仿造巴黎社区，社区房屋的入住率只有 2%。
and it's leading the problem like this five year old billiion dollar fake Paris with occupancy rate only 2%,
而且这些问题还在不断加剧。
and the problems only are getting worse.
简单的供求理论已经被 "先盖，后卖" 所取代。
The simple supply and demand theory has been replaced by "build now, sell later" economics.
这导致有超过 6400万空置的房屋，全中国至少有
11 个大规模的空置鬼城。
That's led to over 64 million empty homes and at least 11 massive empty ghost towns across the country.
象内蒙古的康巴什新区，
Places like Kangbashi District in China's Inner Mongolia,
康巴什新区于 2004年开工建造，花费高达 50亿美元，
Kangbashi was built in 2004, with cost as many as high 5 billion dollars,
现在完全停工了。
and it's a complete bust.
设计目标是容纳一百万人，却只有 3万人入住。
Designed to hold 1 million people, it has a population only 30,000.
巴特尔是一位退休的城市工人，也是新区中基本
不需要的出租车司机之一。
Meet Bater, a retired city co-worker and one of the only cab-drivers in a town that bearly needs any cab at all.
这些都是新建的楼房，是吧？
So, these are all really new buildings, right?
会如何处理所有这些盖了一半的高楼？
What's going to happen to all these half-built high-rises?
这些都是工程只进行了一半的高楼，现在完全荒置了。
There are buildings that are mid-construction, that are now just completely abandoned
in addition to    and also completely abandoned.
康巴什新区是一个令人震惊的选址。
Kangbashi is a stunning site.
一栋接着一栋，大规模的高楼，有些完工了，
多数却都没有完工。
block after block, massive high-rise buildings, some finished, most unfinished,
这块土地用来拍摄大浩劫后的科幻电影会是一个完美的选址。
and none of more than 2 or 3 tenets, a perfect location for a post-apocalypse design fiction film.
但显然不适合用来建造一个城市。
but apparently, a really bad location for a city.
当在这座新城走动时，感觉这里过于现实了，
So it was too realistic when you walk around the city,
在外围郊区能看到这类没有完工的开发。
and there just endless developments where you see this on the outside.
都是宏伟的设计、各类方案，楼很漂亮，我喜欢住在那。
just grand designs, schemes, it's beautiful, I'd love to live here.
但是要把头缩回到这些脚手架后面。
but then you just pull your head right behind this scaffold thing.
这种现实和当初计划的情况相距甚远。
and it's so far from what they have planned.
我们采访一位当地的调查记者，看看在现代中国，
这类大规模的空置新区是如何在现实中成为可能的。
We talk to a local investigate reporter about how realistic this massive is even possible in modern China.
这是小的样本房间，现在就调查一下。
this small sample size, research it right now.
好的，继续往前，看看那间房，没有人住。
ok, go ahead, call that one, no one lives in.
我们已经下了四层楼了，还没见到住户。
so we've come down 4 floors, and so far, no resident.
多数的房门都还用板围着呢。
most of the doors are still boarded up.
想再近距离，看看猜猜，一个超自然的泡温泉的房间？
Oh, you got wanna so close, watch and guess, supernatural spa room?
很可能是个放棺材的房间？
could be as fuck a coffin room?
这是你们猜的，你们去钉钉子吧。
and that was your guess, you nail with.
我们在这巨大的楼房中游荡却没被处罚，周围也有很多建筑。
We walk around this place with impunity in this gigantic building and a bunch of neighbourhood ones.
一个人也没有！这里绝对是没有人！
There's no one, absolutely no one here.
我们想知道，人到底是怎么卖这个公寓，怎么卖这类地方。
We want to know how the hell someone sells the apartment, sell the place like this.
我们拜访一位当地的房地产中介来得到解答。
So we met up a local real estate broker to get the pitch.
非常好，透光好，要在曼哈顿有这么一栋公寓，你就发了。
Very nice, bright, this apartmennt in Manhattan, you
看那边，至少有两家、四家居民，是吧？
Look there at least two, four residents over there, right?
建造这个地方有过担忧吗？
Was there ever any concern that this place being built
你看看周围，没人能确定这个地方是用来出售的。
that no one, you look around, not really sure this place is pending out.
我们是否应该重新思考这件事呢？
Should we maybe rethink this thing?
我们知道，这些满满的建筑会带来严重的后果。
We knew that there has to be serious consequences to all of these filled construction.
我们与 Jame Chanos 坐下来谈谈，他是杰出的现金基金经理。
So we sat down with Jame Chanos, a prominent cash fund manager,
谈谈这些鬼城的当前和潜在的恶劣后果。
to talk about the current and potential fallout for these ghost cities.
我们观察中国大约有3年半了。
We began looking at China about 3.5 years ago.
我们当时试图分析理解，在几代人里最大的经济衰退潮中，
and we were trying to figure out how was that the global commodity's market were doing so well
全球商品市场是如何运行的如此好的。
in the teeth of the biggest recession in generations.
当开始工作时，我们意识到，就幅度和占地面积而言，
就这个世界上最大的建筑场地而言，
and its when we did our work we realize we are looking for something was pretty much unprecedented
我们正在观察的是一种在很大程度上前所未有的现象。
in terms of the scope and size of basically the world's largest construction site.
在 2009年年底，中国的建筑已经有 56亿平方米的地产，
At the end of 09, China had 5.6 billion square metres of property in the construction,
相当于中国的每个男人、女人、小孩都能有一个 5步长，
5步宽的房间。
that equaled to 5 feet x  5 feet office cubic for every man and women and children in China.
地方政府的基本思路就是，抢占土地，将土地周围的房屋全都拆迁，
Basically, local governments for very very little compensation are seizing the land,
然后开发盖高楼，只给当地居民非常非常少的补偿款。
bulldozing the homes around that land, and then developing high-rises.
这就是财富的一种转移，
That's just simply a transfer of wealth,
被转移财富的数目估计多大 5万亿美元。
and the number is estimated to be as much as 5 trillion dollars US.
在康巴什新区，只要我们同意隐藏他们的身份，
找到想倾诉他们拆迁安置经历的人并不难。
In Kangbashi, it wasn't hard to find people willing to tell their own stories of displacement
as long as we agree to keep their identities hidden.
即使已经没有什么可以失去的东西，
他们仍旧生活在惧怕当地政府的氛围中。
Even with nothing left to lose, they were still living in fear of the local government.
但这不是全部，不仅底层的农民失去了他们的土地，
But it didn't stop there, not only with lower class farmers essentially keep off their land,
连中国的中产阶层也亏损了。
but China's middle class has lost out as well.
对这处房地产的投资，得到回报的希望越来越渺茫。
Investing in this real estate with increasingly bleak prospects of return.
房地产投资过热，因为在美国房地产泡沫的最高峰时，
建设投入占总 GDP 的 16%，占 1/6。
It turned to overstate because at the peak of our bubble, construction got to about 16% of GDP, for 1/6.
而中国近 3年的房地产，一直占 GDP 的一半，是美国的 3倍。
It's been running 50% in China now for 3 years, 3 times of our level.
我们的经济交易被认为是支撑国家经济的底线，
而不是一个公司的底线，
Any entity that relies on a series of one of our transactions on economic
任何单位实体如果依赖于我们这一系列交易的某一项，
都将陷入大麻烦。
known as to bolster the country's bottom line, not a company's bottom line, is headed for big trouble.
更糟的是，中国仍在建设大规模的工程，
Making matters worse, China is still building mass projects
这些工程最终会变成康巴什新区一样的鬼城。
that are destined to become ghost towns just like Kangbashi.
事实上，在天津，一个仿造的曼哈顿金融区现在正在施工中。
In fact, a replica of Manhattan financial district, Tianjin, is under construction right now.
看起来，似乎是中国要么不理解鬼城为世界经济带来的问题，
It's as if China either doesn't understand its ghost cities are problematic for the world economy,
要么仅仅是忽略问题。
or they're just choosing to ignore it.
中美经济比过去越来越融合在一体了，
China and US are more and more integrated than ever before.
因此，如果中国经济跌倒崩溃，这对美国商业来讲也是坏消息。
So if China see economies falling to crash, that's going to be bad news for American business.
几年前，我观察第二大经模型，试图了解其中的奥妙，
A few years ago, I call the second economic model, try to know the hell,
结果是，我觉得我们必须得给出建议，作为国家整体，
这是一个将带来大麻烦的现象。
and it end out, I guess we'd have to advise that saying it's a big trouble thing as a nation.